<!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <meta name="generator" content="HTML Tidy, see www.w3.org" />
    <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=ISO-8859-1" />
    <base href="http:/mitgcm.org" />

    <!-- Hinting for menu generation -->
    <meta name="add_name_0" content="News" />
    <meta name="add_name_1" content="" />
    <meta name="add_name_2" content="" />
    <meta name="add_title" content="News" />
    <!-- Hinting for menu generation -->

<style type="text/css">
 span.c2 {font-size: 110%}
 div.c1 {text-align: center}
</style>
  </head>

  <body>

    <p>The <b>MITgcm</b> (<b>MIT</b> <b>G</b>eneral <b>C</b>irculation
      <b>M</b>odel) is a numerical model designed for study of the
      atmosphere, ocean, and climate. Its non-hydrostatic formulation
      enables it to simulate fluid phenomena over a wide range of
      scales; its adjoint capability enables it to be applied to
      parameter and state estimation problems. By employing fluid
      isomorphisms, one hydrodynamical kernel can be used to simulate
      flow in both the atmosphere and ocean.</p>

    <p>You are welcome to <a href="http://mitgcm.org/source_code.html">
      download</a> and use MITgcm.</p>

    <p>Papers charting the development of MITgcm <a
      href="http://paoc.mit.edu/cmi/publications.htm">can be found here.
      </a></p>

    <hr align="center" size="1" width="75%" />

    <div class="c1"><br /><span class="c3"><b>News</b></span></div>

      <!--
      
      To add News items, please copy the following block outside these comments
      and replace the ===DATE=== and ===MESSAGE=== place-holders with your date
      and your text:

      <p><b>===DATE===&nbsp;:</b><br /></p>
        <blockquote>
          ===MESSAGE===<br /><br />
        </blockquote>

      -->

      <p><b>Sep 24, 2004&nbsp;:</b><br /></p>
      <blockquote>
	MITgcm is now able to write and (to a lesser extent) read NetCDF files.
	The framework (the "MNC" package) has been tested by numerous developers
	on literally dozens of machines and, for the past month, has been a
	working part of our standard verification suite.
	
	We encourage MITgcm users (especially new users) to try out the MNC
	package since tqhe model output is now much easier to read and
	understand.  For further NetCDF information please see:
	<ul>
	  <li><a href="http://mitgcm.org/pelican/online_documents/node234.html">
	    Manual entry for the MNC package.</a></li> <li><a
	    href="http://mitgcm.org/pipermail/mitgcm-support/2004-September/002589.html">
	    Directions for installing NetCDF</a></li>
	</ul>
      </blockquote>

    <p><b>May 20, 2004 at 05:01 EDT&nbsp;:</b><br /></p>
    
      <blockquote>
	Congratulations to Ed and Boo on the birth this
	morning of a 7lb 1oz, baby girl, 
	<a href="http://eddy.csail.mit.edu/gallery/Alex-Arrives">Alexandra Sophia</a>.
	<br /><br />
      </blockquote>
      
    <p><b>April 13, 2004&nbsp;:</b><br /></p>
      <blockquote>
	A new movie by Dimitris Menemenlis and Chris Henze shows ice dynamics
	over the North Pole. The viscous-plastic behavior of ice sheets subject
	to wind forcing and ocean currents can be clearly seen in the
	translucent ice-sheet. The movie can be downloaded from <a
	href="movies/ice_03.mpg"> here</a> (this one is 91MB!).  A set of web
	pages with summary information regarding MITgcm simulations being
	carried out in the ECCO high resolution global ocean state estimation
	initiative can be found <a href="http://ecco.jpl.nasa.gov/cube_sphere">
	here</a>.
      </blockquote>

    <p><b>March 26, 2004 at 01:38 EST&nbsp;:</b><br /></p>
    
      <blockquote>
	Congratulations to Alistair and Sonya on the birth this
	morning of a 7lb 3oz, 19.5 inches long baby girl, Ariane Jade.
	<br /><br />
      </blockquote>

    <p><b>January 22, 2004&nbsp;:</b><br /></p>

        <blockquote>
          A spectacular movie by Chris Henze of NASA AMES beautifully captures an 
          eddy permitting expanded cube sphere MITgcm simulation being carried out, 
          as part of the <a href=http://www.ecco-group.org>ECCO</a> project, by 
          Dimitris Menemenlis and others at JPL with help from core MITgcm team members 
          and staff from NASA AMES. The animation 
          shows the speed of ocean currents at 15m depth from the simulation, it can be 
          downloaded <a href=news/cube_6.mpg>here</a> (its 47MB 
          but worth waiting for!). A second animation with different perspectives and 
          rotation can be downloaded <a href=news/cube_7.mpg>here</a>.
          As described <a href=news/agu_2004/menemenlis_et_al.pdf>here</a> Dimitris Menemenlis
          will be presenting aspects of this calculation at AGU in Portland.
          A list of some other AGU 2004 presentation abstracts related to MITgcm can be
          found <a href=news/agu_2004>here</a>.
        </blockquote>

    <p><b>December 9th 2003&nbsp;:</b><br /></p>

	<blockquote>
	  The new continuous testing page at <a
          href="http://mitgcm.org/testing.html">
          http://mitgcm.org/testing.html</a> provides information on the status
          of the latest development code. The page shows summary pass/fail
          ratios for the MITgcm regression tests on various platforms.  Details
          on the platforms being tested and detailed information on the status
          of individual regression tests can be viewed from links on the test
          page.  <br /><br />
        </blockquote>

    <p><b>October 27th 2003&nbsp;:</b><br /></p>

	<blockquote>
      <b><a href="http://paoc.mit.edu/cmi/">MIT Climate Modeling Initiative
	      (CMI)</a></b> web pages introduce the MITgcm model, its
	      applications, and the development team.<br /><br />
        </blockquote>
    
    <p><b>October 21st 2003&nbsp;:</b><br /></p>

	<blockquote>
	  MITgcm and ECCO-JPL team <b><a
	    href="http://www.sgi.com/newsroom/press_releases/2003/october/linux.html">
	    feature as showcase application</a></b> in NASA-SGI large shared
	    memory system program.<br /><br />
        </blockquote>
	
  </body>
</html>

